[
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is true about veteran nuclear scientist Rajagopala Chidambaram, who recently passed away?",
        "options": [
            "He played a pivotal role in India's nuclear tests in 1975 and 1998.",
            "He served as the Director-General of ISRO.",
            "He passed away at AIIMS Hospital in New Delhi.",
            "He was associated with the development of India's first geo-stationary satellite.",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "He played a pivotal role in India's nuclear tests in 1975 and 1998."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two organizations partnered to foster innovation and strengthen the startup ecosystem in India?",
        "options": [
            "NITI Aayog and Startup India",
            "DPIIT and Startup Policy Forum (SPF)",
            "Ministry of Commerce and Industry and FICCI",
            "Ministry of Finance and SIDBI",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "DPIIT and Startup Policy Forum (SPF)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following warships is NOT part of the Indian Navy's Republic Day parade tableau?",
        "options": [
            "INS Surat",
            "INS Vagsheer",
            "INS Nilgiri",
            "INS Vikrant",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "By which year is India aiming to end tuberculosis (TB) under the national TB control initiatives?",
        "options": [
            "2023",
            "2025",
            "2021",
            "2024",
            "2030"
        ],
        "answer": "2025"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization is conducting the National Science Drama Festival 2024-25?",
        "options": [
            "National Science Council of Museums",
            "Ministry of Science and Technology",
            "National Institute of Technology Pune",
            "Niti Aayog",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "National Science Council of Museums"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which platform is providing multilingual access in 11 languages at Mahakumbh Prayagraj 2025?",
        "options": [
            "DigiLocker",
            "UMANG App",
            "Bhashini",
            "Aarogya Setu",
            "Kumbham"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhashini"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two Indian cities were recently added to the Global Wetland Cities list for integrating wetland preservation into their urban plans?",
        "options": [
            "Kolkata and Ahmedabad",
            "Indore and Udaipur",
            "Jaipur and Bhopal",
            "Chandigarh and Hyderabad",
            "None of the abocve"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which authority is responsible for registering Local Cable Operators (LCOs) under the amended Cable Television Network Rules, 1994?",
        "options": [
            "Ministry of Communications (MoC)",
            "Department of Telecommunication (DoT)",
            "Ministry of Information and Broadcasting (MIB)",
            "Ministry of Electronics and Information Technology (MeitY)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Ministry of Information and Broadcasting (MIB)"
    },
    {
        "question": "After the creation of two new Reserve Battalions, what will be the total number of CISF battalions?",
        "options": [
            "13",
            "15",
            "18",
            "20",
            "27"
        ],
        "answer": "15"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company introduced a dedicated Post-Retirement Benefit (PRB) Cell to streamline post-retirement services for its employees?",
        "options": [
            "South Eastern Coalfields Limited (SECL)",
            "Coal India Limited",
            "NTPC Limited",
            "Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited (BHEL)",
            "ONGC"
        ],
        "answer": "South Eastern Coalfields Limited (SECL)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization expanded its fellowships to include non-scientists in its 2025 Fellow list?",
        "options": [
            "Indian National Science Academy (INSA)",
            "Indian Science Congress Association (ISCA)",
            "Indian Academy of Sciences (IAS)",
            "Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Indian National Science Academy (INSA)"
    },
    {
        "question": "When will the first Lokpal Day be celebrated?",
        "options": [
            "14th January 2025",
            "15th January 2025",
            "16th January 2025",
            "17th January 2025",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Cabinet approved setting up the 8th Pay Commission to revise the salaries of central government employees and pensioners. How many employees and pensioners will be affected by it?",
        "options": [
            "49 lakh employees and 65 lakh pensioners",
            "50 lakh employees and 71 lakh pensioners",
            "45 lakh employees and 60 lakh pensioners",
            "66 lakh employees and 55 lakh pensioners",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Department of Administrative Reforms and Public Grievances has released the scheme guidelines for the National e-Governance Awards 2025. The Awards will consist of a Trophy, Certificate, and an incentive of Rs. ______ for Gold Awardees and Rs. ______ for Silver Awardees.",
        "options": [
            "5 lakhs, 3 lakhs",
            "10 lakhs, 7 lakhs",
            "15 lakhs, 10 lakhs",
            "10 lakhs, 5 lakhs",
            "7 lakhs, 3 lakhs"
        ],
        "answer": "10 lakhs, 5 lakhs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Name the initiative launched to empower elected women representatives from Panchayati Raj institutions:",
        "options": [
            "Training Women Leaders Program",
            "Empowering Women in Governance",
            "Women Empowerment in Panchayats",
            "Panchayat Se Parliament",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Panchayat Se Parliament"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Faral Sakhi Initiative, launched by the Mira Bhayandar Municipal Corporation in collaboration with the Women Entrepreneurship Platform (WEP) of NITI Aayog, aims to empower women entrepreneurs by providing training and support for which of the following activities?",
        "options": [
            "Tailoring and garment manufacturing",
            "Production and sale of traditional festive snacks",
            "Handicrafts and artisanal products",
            "Organic farming and agriculture",
            "Beauty and wellness services"
        ],
        "answer": "Production and sale of traditional festive snacks"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization has given preliminary consent to sponsor the 38th National Games being hosted by Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
            "Oil and Natural Gas Corporation (ONGC)",
            "Hindustan Petroleum Corporation Limited (HPCL)",
            "Bharat Petroleum Corporation Limited (BPCL)",
            "Indian Oil Corporation (IOC)",
            "BHEL"
        ],
        "answer": "Indian Oil Corporation (IOC)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Name the India's OTT aggregator with which has BSNL partnered and launched IFTV Pilot in order to bolster inclusive digital connectivity and entertainment for every Indian in UP East?",
        "options": [
            "Zee5",
            "SonyLIV",
            "Hotstar",
            "OTTplay",
            "JioCinema"
        ],
        "answer": "OTTplay"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary goal of the Indian Sustainable Natural Rubber (iSNR) initiative?",
        "options": [
            "To prevent deforestation and support sustainable rubber production",
            "To increase the yield of rubber trees",
            "To focus on enhancing rubber product exports",
            "To reduce the cost of rubber production via supply-chain management",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "To prevent deforestation and support sustainable rubber production"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which initiative was launched by Shri Jayant Chaudhary to empower underserved communities through skill development?",
        "options": [
            "Vocational Training Workshops",
            "Solar-Powered Skill Vans",
            "Digital Education Hubs",
            "Green Energy Skill Program",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Solar-Powered Skill Vans"
    },
    {
        "question": "From which age bracket did the NFHS 4 data reveal about 5% of women undergoing hysterectomy?",
        "options": [
            "15-24 years",
            "25-49 years",
            "50-60 years",
            "Above 60 years",
            "75-90 years"
        ],
        "answer": "25-49 years"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the theme of the Grameen Bharat Mahotsav 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Empowering Villages through Technology",
            "Building a Resilient Rural India for a Viksit Bharat 2047",
            "Economic Transformation through Cooperatives",
            "Sustainable Agriculture for Rural Development",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Building a Resilient Rural India for a Viksit Bharat 2047"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization received Foreign Contribution Regulation Act (FCRA) approval from the Union Ministry of Home Affairs for receiving foreign funds?",
        "options": [
            "Central Tibetan Administration",
            "Tibetan Youth Congress",
            "Tibetan Government-in-Exile",
            "His Holiness the Dalai Lama Charitable Trust",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "His Holiness the Dalai Lama Charitable Trust"
    },
    {
        "question": "By which year does India aim to achieve 500 gigawatts of non-fossil fuel-based energy capacity?",
        "options": [
            "2025",
            "2030",
            "2026",
            "2028",
            "2035"
        ],
        "answer": "2030"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary objective of the recently launched 'PLI Scheme 1.1' for the steel industry?",
        "options": [
            "Promoting export-oriented steel production",
            "Boosting small-scale steel industries in rural areas",
            "Establishing new research centers for advanced metallurgy",
            "Enhancing steel production through Production Linked Incentives",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Enhancing steel production through Production Linked Incentives"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the total expenditure approved by the Union Cabinet for the establishment of the Third Launch Pad (TLP) at ISRO's Satish Dhawan Space Centre, and within how many months is the project expected to be completed?",
        "options": [
            "₹3984 crore; 36 months",
            "₹3984 crore; 48 months",
            "₹4450 crore; 48 months",
            "₹3984 crore; 60 months",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under the National Health Mission (NHM) from 2021 to 2024, how many additional healthcare workers were employed?",
        "options": [
            "8 lakh",
            "10 lakh",
            "12 lakh",
            "15 lakh",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    }
]